<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY app "<application>Yams</application>">
  <!ENTITY appname "Yams">
  <!ENTITY appversion "1.0">
  <!ENTITY authorname "Cătălin Frâncu">
  <!ENTITY date "January 2008">
  <!ENTITY email "<email>cata@francu.com</email>">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "1.0">
]>

<article id="index" lang="en">

  <!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->

  <articleinfo>
    <title>&app; Manual</title>

    <abstract role="description">
      <para>
	Yams is a dice game. Players roll five dice up to three times
	and try to make the best possible combinations.
      </para>
    </abstract>

    <author role="maintainer"> 
      <firstname>Cătălin</firstname> 
      <surname>Frâncu</surname> 
      <affiliation> 
	<address>&email;</address> 
      </affiliation> 
    </author> 

    <copyright>
      <year>2008</year>
      <holder>&authorname;</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>
	Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
	document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License
	(GFDL), Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free
	Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover
	Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  You can find a copy of the
	GFDL at this <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:fdl">link </ulink>
	or online at the <ulink type="http"
	url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html">GNU web page</ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>
	This document, as well as much of the game's layout and
	graphics, are inspired from <ulink type="help"
	url="ghelp:gtali"><application>GNOME
	Tali</application></ulink>, for which the author is deeply
	grateful to Scott Heavner.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

    <legalnotice> 
      <title>Feedback</title> 

      <para>
	To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding the &app;
	application or this manual, please contact &authorname;
	at &email;.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

    <revhistory>
      <revision> 
	<revnumber>&appname; Manual V&manrevision;</revnumber> 
	<date>&date;</date> 
	<revdescription> 
	  <para role="author">
	    &authorname; &email;
	  </para>
	</revdescription> 
      </revision> 
    </revhistory> 

    <releaseinfo>
      This manual describes version &appversion; of &appname;.
    </releaseinfo>
  </articleinfo>


  <!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
       &app; is a dice game involving strategy and luck. You roll five
       dice up to three times and try to create different dice combinations.
       Your two rerolls may include any or all of your dice.
    </para>

    <para>
      &app; can be played in single-player mode or by up to six
      players. There is currently no support for computer opponents.
    </para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="playing">
    <title>Playing &app;</title>
    
    <para>
      When the game starts, click the <guibutton>Roll 1/3</guibutton>
      button to roll all the dice for the first time.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Click on the dice you wish to roll again.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  When you have selected all the dice you wish to reroll,
          press the <guibutton>Roll 2/3</guibutton> button.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  When you have a hand you like or after you have rolled three
          times, click on a cell to write down the points for your
          combination. If your dice do not actually have that
          combination (say if you click on
          the <emphasis>Yams</emphasis> row but you do not have a
          yams), you will get a score of 0. This is referred to
          as <emphasis>cutting</emphasis> a cell.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <sect2 id="keyboard">
      <title>Keyboard shortcuts</title> 

      <para>
	You can select and roll the dice using the keyboard. The
	number keys 1 through 5 select or deselect the corresponding
	die for rerolling and the R key rerolls the selected dice.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Score Sheet</title>

    <para>
      A <emphasis>turn</emphasis> consists of rolling the dice until
      you find the combination you need, up to three times. After each
      turn, you must click on an available cell of the adjacent score
      sheet in order to write down the points for this turn. The &app;
      score sheet consists of six columns and twelve rows. Each column
      can only be completed according to specific rules. The six
      columns are:

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Down:</emphasis> This column can only be filled
	    top-down. For example, you cannot fill
	    the <emphasis>Twos</emphasis> cell until you have filled
	    the <emphasis>Ones</emphasis> cell.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Free Down:</emphasis> You can only fill a cell
	    in this column if you have already filled the
	    corresponding cell in the <emphasis>Down</emphasis> column.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Free Up:</emphasis> You can only fill a cell
	    in this column if you have already filled the
	    corresponding cell in the <emphasis>Up</emphasis> column.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Up:</emphasis> This column can only be filled
	    bottom-up. For example, you cannot fill the <emphasis>Four
	    of a Kind</emphasis> cell until you have filled
	    the <emphasis>Yams</emphasis> cell.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Announced:</emphasis> In order to write down a
	    score in this column, you need
	    to <emphasis>announce</emphasis> the cell that you intend
	    to fill by clicking on it <emphasis>after the first
	    roll.</emphasis> For example, if your first roll is [1, 3,
	    3, 3, 6], you might be tempted to announce a yams on this
	    column. Click the Annnounced Yams cell, then roll twice
	    more in an attempt to make the yams. Regardless of whether
	    you succeed or not, you must click the cell again at the
	    end to write down the score. This can mean a score of 0 if
	    you did not succeed!  If you click in an Announced cell
	    without having announced it first, you will receive a
	    score of 0 in that cell.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Served:</emphasis> You can only write down a
	    score in this column <emphasis>after the first
	    roll</emphasis>. Clicking in a Served cell after two or
	    three rolls will get you a score of 0 in that cell.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      As an example, at the beginning of the game the only available
      cells are the Down Ones, the Up Yams, all the cells on the
      Announced column (provided you announce one after the first
      roll) and all the cells on the Served column (provided you fill
      one after the first roll). If on the first turn you fill the
      Down Ones, then on the second turn the Down Twos and the Free
      Down Ones also become available.
    </para>

    <para>
      The various combinations for the twelve rows are explained in
      the <emphasis>Scoring</emphasis> section. Following these rows
      are the total rows, which show your progress. <emphasis>T1,
      T2</emphasis> and <emphasis>T3</emphasis> indicate the running
      totals for the upper, center and lower section of each
      column. <emphasis>Total</emphasis> indicates the running total
      for the entire column.
     </para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="scoring">
    <title>Scoring</title>

    <para>
      The first four columns score identically, while the Announced
      and Served columns have special bonuses. The order of the dice
      is irrelevant.

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Ones - Sixes:</emphasis> The score for these
	    cells is the sum of the corresponding dice in your
	    hand. For example, if you write the hand [1, 3, 6, 6, 6]
	    in the Down Sixes cell, you will score 18 points (there
	    are three dice of 6).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Max - Min:</emphasis> The score for these cells
	    is simply the sum of the hand. See below how these values
	    are used to compute the value for T2, which is the actual
	    score for the center section.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Straight:</emphasis> You get 15 points for the
	    hand [1, 2, 3, 4, 5] and 20 points for the hand [2, 3, 4,
	    5, 6].
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Full House:</emphasis> Three of the dice have
	    equal values and the remaining two have equal values (all
	    five dice can also be equal, as this is a special kind of
	    full house). The value of the group of three dice dictates
	    the value of the full house: 25 points for Ones, 30 points
	    for Twos, up to 50 points for Sixes.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Four of a Kind:</emphasis> Four of the dice have
	    equal values (the value of the fifth die is ignored). You
	    score 75 points for Ones, 80 points for Twos, up to 100
	    points for Sixes.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Yams:</emphasis> All the dice have equal
	    values. You score 150 points for Ones, 160 points for Twos,
	    up to 200 points for Sixes.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      The rules for computing the column totals are:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>T1</emphasis> is the sum of the Ones through
	    Sixes. If this sum is at least 60, you get a bonus of 30 points.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>T2</emphasis> is the difference between Max and
	    Min mutiplied by the value for Ones. For example, if you
	    scored 28 points in Max, 8 points in Min, and have 3 Ones,
	    then T2 is (28 - 8) * 3 = 60. This scoring method implies
	    that you should try to maximize your Max sum and minimize
	    your Min sum.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>T3</emphasis> is the sum of the lower
	    section. You get a bonus of 100 points if this sum is at
	    least 300, or a bonus of 50 points if the sum is at least
	    150.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Total</emphasis> is simply the sum T1 + T2 + T3.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Grand Total</emphasis> is the running sum of all six
	    columns. At the end of the game, this is your total score.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      There are special rules for the values and totals in the
      Announced and Served columns:

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Bonuses for the Served column are doubled: the upper
	    section bonus is 60, while the lower section bonus is 200
	    or 100.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Served Ones are doubled in value. For example, if you roll
	    [1, 1, 1, 2, 5], you will score 6 points for Ones. This is
	    done so that the T2 value is doubled as well.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Announced Ones through Sixes are doubled, but only if you
	    roll more useful dice in your second or third roll. For
	    example, if your initial hand is [2, 3, 4, 4, 6] and you
	    announce Fours, but you do not roll any more Fours in your
	    subsequent rolls, you still get only 8 points (4 * 2). If
	    you do roll another Four, you double everything and get 24
	    points (4 * 3 * 2).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Announced straights, full houses, four-of-a-kind and
	    yamses score double, but only if you roll more than
	    once. If you announce them and immediately write them down
	    after the first roll, they score their regular points.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    There are no bonuses for the Announced column, since each
	    individual hand is potentially doubled.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If you fill a cell in the Served column after having
	    rolled more than once, you will score 0 points. Likewise,
	    if you fill a cell in the Announced column without having
	    announced anything, you will score 0 points.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="options">
    <title>Game Options</title>

    <para>
      The only configurable options are the number of players and the
      players' names. Note that, after saving the new values, the
      current game will continue with the old players. The new players
      will be used when you begin a new game.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="strategy">
    <title>Game Strategy</title>

    <para>
      These tips are by no means comprehensive, but we have been
      playing this game for over 20 years and we have developed
      certain gut feelings. :)
    </para>

    <para>
      Due to the large number of cells, the game is very flexible,
      particularly in the midgame. Stop after each roll and reconsider
      your options. Perhaps you initially wanted to roll Threes, but
      if your first roll is [2, 5, 5, 6, 6], that's a decent sum of 24
      for the Served Max. Or perhaps you can announce a Full House,
      reroll the Two and hope for a Five or Six.
    </para>

    <para>
      In the top section, if you score three of each figure (three
      Ones, three Twos...), your total will be 63. Since 60 points are
      sufficient to receive the 30-point bonus, you can "afford" to
      lose three points. You can, for example, roll only two Threes,
      or only two Ones and two Twos. Or if you are lucky and roll four
      Twos, you now have five points to spare and can afford to only
      roll two Fives.
    </para>

    <para>
      A served yams is extremely rare. The odds of rolling one are 1
      in 1296 hands, or one every 18 games. We think of the served yams
      as a spare hand for a rainy day. Served four-of-a-kind are not
      much more likely either, although if you're feeling lucky you
      might want to hold on to that cell.
    </para>

    <para>
      When the game begins, your options are very limited. It is
      important to get started on the Down and Up columns. This will
      make many cells available on the two Free columns. So look for
      those Ones and Twos early in the game. Many times you will have
      to cut the Up Yams, sometimes even the Up Four of a Kind, since
      the chances are low that you will actually score a yams during
      the opening hands and it is advisable to move on to easier
      combinations.
    </para>

    <para>
      Keep as many Max and Min cells available for as long as
      possible. When you're shooting for that yams and it just won't
      come, you can still use the hand for a decent score in the Max
      or Min cells.
    </para>

    <para>
      It is much easier to roll a Straight when your initial hand is
      [2, 3, 4, 5, x], since now you have two rolls to try for either
      a One or a Six. When you see this hand in practice, always
      consider going for a Straight.
    </para>
  </sect1>


  <!-- ============= Authors ================================ -->

  <sect1 id="authors">
    <title>Authors</title>

    <para>
      &app; was written by &authorname; &email; &lt;<ulink type="http"
      url="http://catalin.francu.com">http://catalin.francu.com</ulink>&gt;
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ============= Application License ============================= -->

 <sect1 id="license">
   <title>License</title>

   <para>
     This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or
     modify it under the terms of the <ulink type="http"
     url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GNU General Public
     License</ulink> as published by the Free Software Foundation,
     either version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later
     version.
   </para>
    
   <para>
     This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
     but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
     MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the
     GNU General Public License for more details.
   </para>

   <para>
     You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
     along with this program. If not, please visit
     the <ulink type="http"
     url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GNU General Public
     License</ulink> web page.
   </para>
 </sect1>
</article>
